Standard Pyroxoloid Company Records
Standard Pyroxoloid Company Records
1946-1972
Standard Pyroxoloid Corp. (Leominster, Mass.)
3 linear ft.
Collection contains color formulas and product compositions/formulas in the form of typed reports and on 5 x 8" index cards; records of the Standard Pyroxoloid Company and Stanaloid Corporation; and 38 photographs of an unidentified manufacturing facility, date stamped January 16, 1958 (13 are duplicates).
2651155
Biographical History
Standard Pyroxoloid Company was a plastics manufacturer in Leominster, Massachusetts. The Standard Pyroxoloid Company may have evolved into, or been bought out by, the Stanaloid Corporation.
The relationship among the companies named in this collection is unclear and requires further research. The color and product formulas appear to have passed from Du Pont's Arlington Works to Stanaloid Corporation at some time, because the Du Pont name is crossed out and Stanaloid written in. The pieces are assumed to be one collection by virtue of their storage together and similarity of handwriting on the old housing.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Standard Pyroxoloid Company Records contains color formulas and product compositions/formulas, company records, and photographs.
Company records contains the records of the Standard Pyroxoloid Company and of the Stanaloid Corporation.
Photographs contain an unidentified manufacturing facility, date stamped January 16, 1958.
Product compositions/formulas & processing methods contains formulas, including those for colors, in typed report form and on 5 x 8” file cards.
Miscellaneous contains blank stationary and internal use office reports for the Stanaloid Corporation
Related Material
has numerous holdings in the areas of plastics and industrial design. Please refer to for a complete listing. See in particular the
Standard Comb Company Photographs
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Plastics; E. I. du Pont de Nemours & Company. Arlington Works.; Stanaloid Corporation.; Standard Pyroxoloid Corp. (Leominster, Mass.) -- Archives.; Celluloid.; Chemical plants.; Factories.; Nitrocellulose.; Plastics industry and trade.; Product formulas.; Pyralin.; Reports.; Photographs.; Business records.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from National Plastics Center and Museum, 11/06/2008.
Inventory
- Company records
  - Reports, 1946-1949; 1952-1965; documents from various departments; baking, mixing, press polish, Pyroxylin, rod and tube, rolling, seasoning, stuffing, sheeting (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Unidentified manufacturing facility, 16 Jan 1958; images of machinary; 38 photographs (Box 1)
- Product compositions/formulas & processing methods
  - Color formulas & reports: Pyralin no. 52542-53181, 1957; report 53081, "translucent white pearl," includes a material sample, incomplete series (Box 2)
  - Color formulas & reports: Pyralin no. 4112-4122, 1957; incomplete series (Box 3)
  - Color formulas & reports: Pyralin no. 4127-7311, 1957; incomplete series (Box 4)
  - Color formulas & reports: unnumbered, 1957; includes cellulose nitrate sheeting formulas, polyvinyl butyral sheeting by block method process, and a camphor test (Box 5)
  - Color formulas, undated; index cards with color ingredients, raw materials and color information; 200+ index cards (Box 6-7)
- Product Literature
  - Catalogs, 1972; toy catalogs (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous
  - Stanaloid Corporation, 1971-1972; undated; blank analysis and weekly expense reports and blank company stationary, (Box 5)